Good morning. Today's דף daf is טז, tet-zayin, but it's listed where
we're picking up a little bit behind on פו עמוד ב, pe-vav
amud-bet, four lines before the lines get wide.
And אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני. Amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani. So
obviously we're in the middle of a long discussion about תשובה, teshuva,
and as we were discussing right beforehand, you know, the whole fact
that the גמרא Gemara now in the absence of all the עבודה
avoda of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, תשובה teshuva is what you're left
with, maybe תשובה teshuva plus עיצומו של יום כיפור, itzumo shel Yom
Kippur, תשובה teshuva plus death, which leads to the גמרא Gemara trying
to give some type of a structure and parameters in terms of
how תשובה teshuva works under what situations it's effective together with other
things. So now we're also in the middle of just general discussions
about the power of תשובה. teshuva. So let's take a look. אמר
רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן גדולה תשובה. Amar Rabbi Shmuel
bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan gedola teshuva. תשובה teshuva is great שמארכת
שנותיו של אדם, she-ma'arechet shenotav shel adam, it extends your years, שנאמר
shenemar ובשוב רשע מרשעתו חיה הוא יחיה. uvshuv rasha merishato chayo hu
yichye. So when you do תשובה teshuva you will
live. אמר רבי יצחק אמרי במערבא משמיה דרבא בר מרי בוא וראה
שלא כמדת הקדוש ברוך הוא מדת בשר ודם. Amar Rabbi Yitzchak amri
b'ma'arava mishme d'Rabba bar Mari bo u're'e shelo k'middat ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu
middat basar va-dam. Come and see that God's ways are not the
way of flesh and blood. מדת בשר ודם מדת מקניט את חברו
בדברים. Middat basar va-dam middat maknit et chavero bi-dvarim. The way of
flesh and blood is if you hurt somebody with your words, ספק
מתפייס הימנו ספק אין מתפייס הימנו. safek mitpayes heymenu safek ein mitpayes
heymenu. Even if you try to make up, it's doubtful, it's a
question whether he will agree to be appeased or not. ואם תאמר
מתפייס הימנו, ve-im tomar mitpayes heymenu, even if he finally is able
to be appeased and reconciled, ספק מתפייס בדברים ספק אין מתפייס בדברים.
safek mitpayes bi-dvarim safek ein mitpayes bi-dvarim. Sometimes words alone will do
it, I'm sorry, you know, an apology, sometimes it needs something much
more. אבל הקדוש ברוך הוא, aval ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu, but with God,
אדם עובר עבירה בסתר, adam over aveira baseter, even if a person
sins to Him in private, מתפייס הימנו בדברים. mitpayes heymenu bi-dvarim.
It's actually interesting, the word בסתר. baseter. What's בסתר baseter doing here?
And actually בסתר baseter you might expect the context to be ברבים.
barabbim. ברבים בדברים barabbim bi-dvarim almost looks exactly the same word, but
it is clearly בדברים, bi-dvarim, שנאמר shenemar קחו עמכם דברים, kechu imachem
dvarim,
take just with you words. All I ask of you is no
gift, no act, just words, right? ושובו אל ה', v'shuvu el Hashem,
return to God. So instead of קרבנות, korbanot, all you need is
words. ולא עוד אלא שמחזיק לו טובה, velo od ela she-machzik lo
tova,
not only that, you know, that God actually is grateful for it.
It's not like He begrudges it, He's grateful, שנאמר shenemar וקח
טוב, v'kach tov, it'll be something good that you'll do. ולא עוד
אלא שמעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו הקריב פרים, velo od ela she-ma'ale alav
ha-katuv k'ilu hikriv parim, it's like you brought sacrifices, שנאמר ונשלמה פרים
שפתינו, shenemar u-neshalma parim sefatenu,
and sacrifices will be at our lips will satisfy, will lead the
need of sacrifices of oxen as if we, as if we actually
brought sacrifices. שמא תאמר פרי חובה, shema tomar parei chova, lest you
say that though we're talking about oxen of obligation,
you know, you do something out of a sense of obligation, maybe
it's not as great, you gotta do it, תלמוד לומר ארפא משובתם
אוהבם נדבה. talmud lomar erpa meshuvatam ohavam nedava.
I will heal their returning, I will love them as a free
will, as if they are brought a free will sacrifice. So there
are two things that are worth mentioning here. Again, first of all,
the question is what's the sense of בסתר? baseter? Is this God's
greatness that even though the sin is בסתר, baseter, you know, He'll
forgive you in a public way? You don't have חילול השם. chillul
Hashem. Well no, but the sin was בסתר. baseter. And so it
could be that it's not coming to tell you like oh, and
of course He'll do the same if you sin in public, it
could be actually it's excluding the case of public because as we
saw yesterday the whole terrible sin about חילול השם chillul Hashem and
so on. So we're not willing to say that it's necessarily just
as easy if it's a public sin. So that's one just noticing
the word בסתר. baseter. The other thing to notice here is I
guess to the point that I made a minute ago and that
we were talking discussing before the שיעור shiur is the question about
תשובה teshuva as a substitute for sacrifices. So first of all, you
know, it ends by just saying first it says all you need
is words, so like you don't need big ritual and sacrifices. I
see, you know, I'd like to read a lot of this as
a implicit contrast with everything that preceded about all of the עבודה
avoda of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So now all you need is
words, you don't need big ritual, just say your תשובה. teshuva. And
then it is equivalent to the sacrifices. So on the one hand
it might be holding up as the sacrifices as the ideal and
you know this is a substitute, it's equivalent to, but ultimately still
the ideal would be to bring sacrifices. Although it is worth mentioning
the last line where it says not פרי חובה. parei chova. Well
what was all of the עבודה avoda of יום כיפור? Yom Kippur?
All the עבודה avoda of יום כיפור Yom Kippur was פרי חובה.
parei chova. What is all the normal קרבנות korbanot that you bring
when you sin? It's a חטאת, chatat, it's a פרי חובה, parei
chova, well not a פר par but whatever. Anyway, so you know
everything that you normal sacrifices that are needed for the process of
atonement are obligatory. Besides the whole general idea, you know, גדול המצווה
ועושה gadol ha-metzuve v'ose and so on. So the fact that yes,
on the one hand it's being framed as a sacrifice, but on
the other hand it's a different type of a sacrifice as a
נדבה, nedava, to me I think that you know it's not necessarily
saying like oh, you know, this is a this is a substitute,
ideally we'd be doing קרבנות korbanot and חטאות chataot and this and
that, now all we have is תשובה. teshuva. There seems to be
a real underscoring about the power of this itself, although here maybe
equal or greater than that of sacrifices, although here there is a
bit of a tension because it's sort of in the end framing
it as sacrifices, but not as obligatory sacrifices, so we get both
messages going on. What's also worth mentioning in this context is, and
this was what was covered yesterday,
was the whole idea about how this brings healing to the world.
It's not just that it atones for you; the most immediate thing
that we said is it extends your years. There's this broader cosmic
metaphysical power of תשובה. Tshuvah. If anybody has ever read Rav Kook's
אורות התשובה, Orot HaTshuvah, Rav Kook for תשובה Tshuvah is not just
a personal act of not just a personal thing that God allows
you to repent and then forgives you. He sort of sees it
in much more messianic and cosmic terms. It's the world rising, global
תשובה Tshuvah to a higher level and so on. Anyway, without developing
that, but it's just worth noting the way that I see that
that can also parallel themes we discussed when we did the עבודה
Avodah of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, that the עבודה Avodah of יום
כיפור Yom Kippur is not just to atone for the individual sins,
which is really just the שעיר המשתלח, Seir HaMishtaleach, but it's וכיפר
על הקודש מטומאות בני ישראל. VeChiper Al HaKodesh MiTumot Bnei Yisrael. It
cleanses the sanctuary. It has this sort of allows God, it works
for the nation and allows God to dwell with the nation and
cleanses the sin of the sanctuary. Here it's even
bigger; it's sort of universal, it brings healing to the entire world.
So the idea that תשובה, Tshuvah, like the עבודה Avodah of יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, maybe in a way is more powerful than the
עבודה Avodah of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, creates a broader cosmic
metaphysical purity and elevation and bringing us closer to the divine. So
again, I think it's worth thinking as we do this about the
parallels that exist between this
and יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. While we're talking about that,
and I'll maybe repeat this when we get to this part of
the משנה Mishnah later, but it is worth mentioning that the last
line of the משנה, Mishnah, which is sort of that famous one
also made into a song,
אשריכם ישראל לפני מי אתם מטהרים ומי מטהר אתכם אביכם שבשמים, Ashreichem
Yisrael Lifnei Mi Atem Mitaharim Umi Metaher Etchem Avichem Shebashamayim, וזרקתי עליכם
מים טהורים וטהרתם, Vezarakti Aleichem Mayim Tehorim Utetartem, מקוה ישראל ה׳. Mikveh
Yisrael Hashem. So think about how that contrasts to
what we've been talking about by יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. First of
all, the מהרש״א Maharsha already points out the different ways that Rabbi
Akiva is using the word
לפני ה׳ תטהרו. Lifnei Hashem Titharu. The second to last line of
the משנה Mishnah said that יום כיפור Yom Kippur is only מכפר
Mechaper on עבירות שבין אדם למקום Aveirot Shebein Adam LaMakom because it
says מכל חטאתיכם לפני ה׳ Mikol Chatoteichem Lifnei Hashem תטהרו, Titharu, things
you sort of sinned before God תטהרו, Titharu,
but בין אדם לחברו Bein Adam LeChavero not. But Rabbi Akiva not
just agreeing with that but does a twist and says no, no,
no, לפני ה׳ תטהרו, Lifnei Hashem Titharu, by being in the presence
of God that causes purity. לפני מי אתם
מטהרים? Lifnei Mi Atem Mitaharim? Your טהרה Taharah comes because you're לפני
ה׳. Lifnei Hashem. לפני מי? Lifnei Mi? לפני ה׳ תטהרו. Lifnei Hashem
Titharu. מה מקוה מטהר את הטמאים אף הקדוש ברוך הוא מטהר את
ישראל. Mah Mikveh Metaher Et HaTmeim Af HaKadosh Baruch Hu Metaher Et
Yisrael. And basically think about the contrast. On יום כיפור Yom Kippur
when we had the עבודה, Avodah, what did we do? We did
the עבודה, Avodah, we were מטהר, Metaher, we cleansed the מקדש Mikdash
that allowed then God to dwell amongst us. But we did the
cleansing that allowed God to be with us. Rabbi Akiva is saying
in the absence of מקדש Mikdash and all you have is תשובה,
Tshuvah,
you directly present yourself before God. You don't have to do a
prior whole עבודה Avodah to get God to now be with you
and you have to do the cleansing; you present yourself before God
and God cleanses
you. It's an amazing reversal and it's obviously more powerful. We can
directly present ourselves before God on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and then
God will cleanse us. So again, I think it's worth thinking as
we do this about the parallels that exist between this and יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. While we're talking about that, if you think about
what's being said here, not just about the power of תשובה, Tshuvah,
but given everything we said before about the עבודה Avodah of יום
כיפור Yom Kippur and ways in which I think that this is
even, not just oh it's just as good or it's a substitute,
but ways in which this is even more powerful.
Yes, my friend as opposed to the קרבן, Korban, when you do
a
קרבן, Korban, as opposed to
if you take to a מקוה, Mikveh, you can't be טובל ושרץ
בידו.
Tovel
VeSheretz Beyado. So you still need to do a lot more in
some ways.
I did not mean to say that it was easier. The difference
is that קרבנות Korbanot is a ritual whereas תשובה Tshuvah is a
real interior process and really requires real תשובה. Tshuvah. We actually have
the whole question about the וידוי Viduy by the פר Par and
whatever, is the וידוי מעכב Viduy Meakev and all those issues and
so on, and shifts where we saw that the וידוי Viduy was
being raised in the significance of the קרבנות. Korbanot. But yes, that
is the difference, that קרבנות Korbanot is a ritual whereas this is
a real interior process and really requires real תשובה. Tshuvah. So I
don't mean to suggest that it's easier, but in a way there's
something also that's being said here in contrast that's more powerful.
Yes, I've heard those stories
Rabbi Akiva.
חורבן המקדש, churban hamikdash, right, he's always willing to emphasize exactly the
positive. Okay,
so let's take a look now as the גמרא Gemara continues with
this.
Okay,
so right. Well, you know what, I will just say one more
word about that, since I'm not here, I wasn't here yesterday, so
I have to make up for it about רבי, Rebbi, about Michael's
point about רבי, Rebbi, about יום כיפור מכפר Yom Kippur mechaper with
תשובה, teshuvah, without תשובה teshuvah and so on, is the same idea,
like what does רבי Rebbi mean, יום כיפור Yom Kippur is מכפר
mechaper without תשובה? teshuvah? You don't have to do any תשובה? teshuvah?
So on the one hand, רבי Rebbi might be trying to retain
the idea of the יום כיפור Yom Kippur with the קרבנות. korbanot.
Maybe there are some rituals that achieve it, that תשובה teshuvah is
not central, you know, without those rituals, without יום כיפור Yom Kippur
whatever, תשובה, teshuvah, you know, like they said before, well תשובה teshuvah
works for everything, but maybe even without תשובה, teshuvah, you know, maybe
יום כיפור Yom Kippur does something according to רבי Rebbi the same
way קרבנות, korbanot, maybe you had a ritual that was effective even
without the interior process of תשובה. teshuvah. So it is worth again
noting that, you know, in a way that's weird for us, but
in a way that's actually just holding onto a reality that we
had by the קרבנות. korbanot. It is worth noting that the תוספות
ישנים Tosafot Yeshanim asks the question and he says, what, what does
that mean? Like, you know, first of all, the משנה Mishnah says,
you know, תשובה עם יום הכיפורים מכפר. teshuvah im Yom HaKippurim mechaper.
And if you remember yesterday the גמרא Gemara said, but according to
רבי, Rebbi, יום כיפור Yom Kippur does it by itself. So this
is fine. If you, you know, יום כיפור Yom Kippur does it
by itself. If you did, if you, you know, if you did
תשובה teshuvah you need יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but if you had
יום כיפור Yom Kippur you don't need תשובה. teshuvah. So he says
what? So why does the משנה Mishnah say, תשובה עם יום הכיפורים
מכפר עם התשובה? teshuvah im Yom HaKippurim mechaper im hateshuvah? Why do
you have to say עם התשובה? im hateshuvah? So anyway, so the
תוספות ישנים Tosafot Yeshanim says a line. He says, look, it might
be תשובה teshuvah that's מכפר, mechaper, but it doesn't do the whole
job. Like, you know, the line here is, I'll just read it.
He says, now I got to get out my glasses. He says,
he says,
ועוד יש לומר דלרבי נמי צריך תשובה. Ve'od yesh lomar d'leRebbi nami
tzarich teshuvah. It's on where is it?
פ״ה ע״ב Pei Hei amud bet first column near the bottom. דלרבי
נמי צריך תשובה לכפרה גמורה אף על גב דזמן יום הכיפורים למעט
מכרת מכל מקום כפרה גמורה בלא תשובה ליכא.
D'leRebbi nami tzarich teshuvah l'khapparah
gemurah af al gav dzman Yom HaKippurim lema'et mikaret mikol makom kapparah
gemurah belo teshuvah leka. Now what does that mean that you need
a כפרה גמורה? kapparah gemurah? What is it when it's not גמורה?
gemurah? So it's worth noting here a famous point that רב Rav
Soloveitchik makes. He wasn't the only one to make it, but anyway,
it's a very classic part of his lectures in על התשובה Al
HaTeshuvah where he speaks about the idea, the difference between כפרה kapparah
and what he calls טהרה. taharah. If you want to use the
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva phrase לפני מי אתם מיטהרים lifnei mi atem
metaharim and he says, it's one thing to say that a קרבן
korban is מכפר mechaper or יום כיפור Yom Kippur is מכפר, mechaper,
which that means basically cleanses the slate from punishment, that you will
not be punished. It saves you from the consequence. But it does
not mean that it makes you into a better person. How could
a קרבן, korban, how could יום כיפור Yom Kippur by itself transform
who you are as a person, make you from a רשע rasha
into a צדיק? tzaddik? What it could do is it could say,
you won't be punished. You did the thing, check. יום כיפור Yom
Kippur came, check. You're not going to get punished. Okay.
And that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara says is תולה, toleh, right?
That's the... right, that's the idea of תולה toleh and
says, you know, you're protected until you get to the...
to the next stage, exactly. So that's, you know, so that's that
even within רבי Rebbi who holds onto this idea that יום כיפור
Yom Kippur is מכפר mechaper without תשובה, teshuvah, does that mean there's
no function of תשובה? teshuvah? So no, תשובה teshuvah obviously is what's
necessary to transform you as an individual, to make you from a
רשע rasha to a צדיק, tzaddik, to make you a better person
and so on. It's a different question about whether you're going to
get punished for your sins. That maybe certain rituals can get you
out of. So again, that really does raise this question we're talking
about, on the one hand, יום כיפור Yom Kippur and the עבודה
avodah and the rituals switching over to a world of תשובה. teshuvah.
So are we saying that תשובה teshuvah is a weak substitute? Are
we saying תשובה teshuvah is equal? Are we saying תשובה teshuvah is
better, you know, more powerful? Like I said, ways in which it's
more powerful is that it has a cosmic cleansing. The עבודה avodah
cleanses the מקדש. mikdash. תשובה teshuvah maybe is, you know, brings רפואה
לעולם. refuah le'olam. It's cosmic in terms of that power. It's better
that you don't rather have to do the cleansing to allow God
to come, you present yourself before God and then God actually cleanses
you. That's even more powerful. And then of course, as Michael points
out, you know, it's harder to do תשובה. teshuvah. It's not just
going through the motions. There's a real process. And that leads to
the final point about what way is תשובה teshuvah different? תשובה teshuvah
is about personal transformation where some of these rituals, like יום כיפור
Yom Kippur by itself or קרבנות korbanot by itself, might just be
about not being, you know, not being punished. The last thing I'll
just say about that is, and we're going to get to a
גמרא Gemara in a minute about like what happens, will תשובה teshuvah
continue to atone for if you keep on sinning again and again,
which I think is a problem that we often have, like we
do תשובה teshuvah at יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, then we go back.
We do תשובה teshuvah not intentionally, but you know, it's our nature
to go back to our old habit, that even תשובה, teshuvah, we
can talk about, you know, there's a תשובה teshuvah that can be
effective to clean the slate and to achieve atonement and forgiveness from
punishment. And that's not... there's a higher level of תשובה teshuvah that
is really that is really transformative for us as individuals. It's rare
that someone to say that's
the difference. And then there's a תשובה Teshuva that is a sincere
sense of regret and, you know, and וידוי Viduy and and all
of that, and that's genuine even if it doesn't it's not going
to profoundly change you, and that maybe works to achieve, you know,
forgiveness from from punishment without yet getting at the level of personal
transformation. So, yeah.
The idea that the rituals of יום כיפור Yom Kippur could potentially
could result in כפרה Kapara without any personal atonement would seem to
fly in the face of a whole bunch of נביאים. Neviim.
Exactly. I'll talk about I don't want your sacrifices, I want your
זבחים. Zvachim.
Right.
Again, nobody is saying that that's what's desired, but it might be
the fallback for people that are human and sin and so on.
You know? So, but that's also not talking about the process of
תשובה Teshuva and cleansing. That's talking about what the what God wants
from us in terms of of our what service of God is
really about. So I think there's a different focus for that.
Maybe all of this is talking about בין אדם למקום? Ben Adam
Lamakom? Maybe all of this is talking about בין אדם למקום, Ben
Adam Lamakom, but then there's clearly בין אדם לחברו.
Ben Adam L'chavero.
No, but I think it's different. When God when the פסוק Pasuk
says למה לי רוב זבחיכם יאמר ה׳ שבעתי אילים וחלב מריאים, Lama
li rov zivcheichem yomar Hashem savati eilim v'chelev meri'im, and you know,
ודם פרים וחלב מריאים, v'dam parim v'chelev meri'im, it doesn't mean like
oh, these don't achieve atonement. What it means is that this isn't
true עבודת השם. Avodas Hashem. It's talking about more that daily sense
of עבודת השם Avodas Hashem than the question of atonement.
Yeah. We speak of ייסורין ממרקין. Yisurin memarkin. ממרקין, Memarkin, they scour,
they purge us. Is that different than just checking off like you
did this, does that really erase?
Well,
that, yeah, gets to that question about like that that's sort of
like, you know, it's it's maybe a good word is scours. You
ever try to scour a pot, especially a טשולנט Cholent pot after
שבת? Shabbos? You can be working with that steel wool really, really
hard and you still got those those that black stuff isn't coming.
But I think that's like a good image for this. It's like
you're scouring and it causes a certain amount of like friction and
pain and whatever and it's still not going to totally cleanse. Scours.
Okay, let's get back to the גמרא. Gemara. Okay.
Okay. תניא היה רבי מאיר אומר גדולה תשובה שבשביל יחיד שעשה
תשובה Tanya haya Rabbi Meir omer gedola Teshuva she-bishvil yachid she-asa Teshuva
and here gets again to this cosmic aspect of it, right, for
an individual who does תשובה, Teshuva, מוחלין לכל העולם כולו, mochlin l'chol
ha'olam kulo, brings מחילה Mechila for the whole world. Now, again, you
could say like יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, right, it's one כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol doing it for everyone, but nevertheless, you know, there are
even there קרבנות ציבור Korbanot tzibur and it's for the and it's
somewhat seen as a communal act. Here, look how powerful it is,
one person does תשובה, Teshuva, brings מחילה Mechila for the whole world.
I don't know, you know, I'm not God's scorekeeper. שנאמר ארפא משובתם
אוהבם נדבה כי שב אפי ממנו She-ne'emar erpeh meshuvatam ohavam nedava ki
shav api mimenu in the singular. Because my anger went away from
him singular, I will he I will heal their to their returnings
in the plural. Okay. מהם לא נאמר אלא ממנו. Me-hem lo ne'emar
ela mimenu. Okay. Now היכי דמי בעל תשובה? Heichi dami ba'al Teshuva?
How do you measure, how do you determine that somebody has really
done תשובה? Teshuva? אמר
רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, I mean, this isn't for us to
judge other people, presumably for somebody to judge themselves. כגון שבאת לידו
דבר עבירה פעם ראשונה ושניה וניצל הימנה. Kegon she-ba'at l'yado davar aveira
pa'am rishona u'shniya v'nitzal heimena.
Somebody sinned and then he was presented with the opportunity to sin
not just once, like especially, you know, מוצאי יום כיפור Motzei Yom
Kippur we're real good, we'll resist, you know, the first time, but
even the second time you're able to have that strength to continue
to resist, you know, that is a בעל תשובה. Ba'al Teshuva. מאחוי
רב יהודה, Machvi Rav Yehuda, באותה אשה באותו פרק באותו מקום. ba'oso
isha ba'oso perak ba'oso makom.
You're saved by, you know, as if by God.
Oh, that's an interesting point I hadn't thought of, rather than focusing
it on your
the strength of your character. Right.
I think the גמרא Gemara uses the
passive if I remember correctly. That's a good point. If you look
at the ב״ח, Bach, the ב״ח Bach has an alternative גירסא, girsa,
ופירש הימנה. u-piraish heimena. The ב״ח Bach's גירסא girsa is you separate
from it. So that's an excellent point, is that your תשובה Teshuva
means that divinely God will save you or do you have now
the strength of character to stop not doing. מאחוי רב יהודה, Machvi
Rav Yehuda, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda sort of signaled באותה אשה באותו
פרק באותו מקום. ba'oso isha ba'oso perek ba'oso makom. It has to
be like the exact same circumstances, that's the real test. The same
woman who you cheated with before and at the same time of
year, like, you know, and at the same place, so all the
opportunities are there. רש״י Rashi says it's not just, you know, you
know, the question, A could be just like the same opportunities, it's
interesting רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says
באותה אשה ba'oso isha like second third narrow line, he says שבעתה
עבירה ובאותו פרק מתוך שדומה מכל וכל לזמן שנכשל בה כבר יצרו
מתגבר עליו ואומר לו ראה פלוני באותו מקום באותו פרק הוא קום
עשה מה שעשית כבר. she-ba'asa aveira u-v'oso perek mitoch she-domeh mi-kol v'chol
l'zman she-nichshal bah kvar yitzro mitgaber alav v'omer lo re'eh ploni ba'oso
makom ba'oso perek hu kum asei mah she-asita kvar.
So basically רש״י Rashi talks about about like, you know, you fall
into your habitual ways, like it's just if it's the exact same
circumstances, it's so easy to fall back into that pattern. So it's
not just like it's the same יצר הרע, Yetzer Hara, it's the
same degree of temptation. So basically Rashi's talks about like you know
you fall into your habitual ways, like it's just if it's the
exact same circumstances, it's so easy to fall back into that pattern.
So it's not just like it's the same יצר הרע, yetzer hara,
it's the same degree of temptation, but there's also the power of
habit. Not only are you tempted in the same degree and you
have the same opportunity, but it's so easy to fall back into
your habitual ways and you still resist it.
Yes, it is interesting the assumption of
using a woman as the classic example of sin. Yes. I'm not
actually convinced—it is interesting the assumption of using a woman as the
classic example of sin. Yes.
I'm not sure—I'm not convinced that ניצל nitzal is necessarily
passive in this context. In other words, להציל l'hatzil I would say,
if you ניצל nitzal might be like one escapes.
Yeah, I don't know, I would imagine there's a reflexive element to
it. But okay, anyway, so let's keep on going. It
says אמר רב יהודה רב רמי, Amar Rav Yehuda Rav Rami, Rav
shows a contradiction. כתיב, Ktiv, one פסוק pasuk says אשרי נשוי פשע
כסוי חטאה, Ashrei nesui pesha kisui chata'ah, praise is to the one
that is lifted up of sin, forgiven of sin, who covers up
his sin. וכתיב, U'chtiv, מכסה פשעיו לא יצליח, Mechaseh pesha'av lo yatzliach,
one who hides his iniquities will not succeed. So are you supposed
to hide your sins or not? So one could of course say
the difference is whether you've done תשובה teshuva or not, it's hiding
your sins while you're still sinning. But the גמרא Gemara assumes that
it's both in the process of תשובה, teshuva, so how does it
reconcile it? לא קשיא, Lo kashya, this isn't difficult. הא בחטא מפורסם
הא בחטא שאינו מפורסם. Ha b'cheit mefursam ha b'cheit she'eino mefursam. If
it's a public sin, then you need to expose it and do
תשובה teshuva publicly. People have already known you've sinned, they need to
now see the תשובה teshuva being done publicly, they need you to
take also public accountability for it. If it's a private sin, then
by doing תשובה teshuva in public you are—it's a חילול השם, chillul
Hashem, like you're announcing to people that you've sinned and it could
also be seen as giving license to it or whatever. So if
you've sinned in private, do תשובה teshuva in private, don't make it
public your apology and your תשובה. teshuva.
That's one answer. רב זוטרא בר טוביה אמר רב נחמן, Rav Zutra
bar Tuvia amar Rav Nachman, כאן בעבירות שבין אדם לחברו וכאן בעבירות
שבין אדם למקום. kan b'aveirot she'bein adam l'chaveiro v'kan b'aveirot she'bein adam
l'Makom. If it's between you and God, fine, keep it private. If
it's between you and another person, make it public. Why? I mean,
maybe it was initially done private, but presumably there again, when it's
done to another person, the concerns about a חילול השם chillul Hashem
to be talking about your sin are outweighed by the concerns about
the larger communal lesson. Oh my God, this person did such and
such and now he's doing תשובה teshuva and he's made a public
apology, and you know, and the fact that—and how it affects other
people and the sin that was done to other people
is something that that sort of those concerns
outweigh the concerns about that it'll seem like a חילול השם chillul
Hashem to admit that you've—to announce the fact that you've sinned. If
you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says
עבירות שבין אדם לחברו יגלה לרבים שיבקשו ממנו שימחול לו. aveirot she'bein
adam l'chaveiro yigaleh l'rabim she'yivakshu mimenu she'yimchol lo. So רש"י Rashi says
a little different than I'm saying. רש"י Rashi is saying that if
you sin to another person you might need to publicize it because
you might
need—if you sin to many people, you certainly need to publicize it,
but even to an individual you might need to like get people
to speak to the other guy on your behalf, you know, and
try to come to your aid to achieve the מחילה mechila as
we know that מחילה mechila is part of it. But even without
that I would have argued that like there's always this balance, right?
Do you—you know, it's sort of like in a little way it's
like the famous debate that was between the חפץ חיים Chafetz Chaim
and רבי ישראל סלנטר, Rabbi Yisrael Salanter, which is if you told
לשון הרע lashon hara about somebody and they don't know, are you
allowed to ask the person מחילה? mechila? Because in the process of
asking מחילה mechila you're hurting the person, because you're letting them know
that you told לשון הרע lashon hara about them, right? So do
you have—and sometimes that's an important lesson in general about apologies. Sometimes
your apology is to make yourself feel better, not really the other
person. Anyway, so here the same thing is, you know, if you
go out and you publicly say oh I did this terrible sin,
so there's the public gains from it, they learn oh my gosh
look at this person he's doing תשובה, teshuva, we could all learn
from it.
And someone says, "Yeah, but he doesn't have to say which sin
he did."
Alright, yeah, maybe. Anyway, maybe. Anyway, you know, so I think that
there's something to be learned but there's also a sense like if
people talk about their sins, you know, maybe it's—it's present—you know, maybe
it's—there's an aspect of חילול השם, chillul Hashem, it gives a certain
degree of a license. How do we counter—how do we weigh those
issues? So to me there's something very resonant about the fact that
when you're hurting other people and the type of sins that can
hurt other people, so the, you know, so sort of the—the question
about the lessons to the larger public outweigh the חילול השם chillul
Hashem types of concerns in those cases.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues, let's take a look.
So בין אדם לחברו bein adam l'chaveiro basically you're supposed to say.
You're supposed to, according to this, you're supposed to do תשובה teshuva
in public or let people know that you've sinned.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. תניא, Tanya, רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yosei b'Rabbi Yehuda omer,
אדם עובר עבירה פעם ראשונה מוחלין לו, Adam over aveira pa'am rishona
mochlin lo, a person sins once it's forgiven for him. שניה מוחלין
לו, shniya mochlin lo, second time it's forgiven. שלישית מוחלין לו, shlishit
mochlin lo, third time it's forgiven. רביעית אין מוחלין לו, revi'it ein
mochlin lo, fourth time it's not forgiven. שנאמר, Shene'emar, כה אמר ה'
על שלשה פשעי ישראל ועל ארבעה לא אשיבנו, Koh amar Hashem al
shlosha pishei Yisrael v'al arba'ah lo ashivenu, for three maybe like I
would have forgiven, for four I will no longer forgive, I will
no longer return. ואומר, V'omer, the פסוק pasuk says הן כל אלה
יפעל אל, Hen kol eleh yifa'el E-l, all of these God will
do פעמים שלוש עם גבר, pa'amayim shalosh im gaver, two and three
times with a person. And the end of the פסוק pasuk is
or the next פסוק pasuk is he'll return him. from the depths
and from death and so on, I mean two to three times
God will save you from the consequence but not four times. Now
מאי ואומר, mai ve'omer, why do you need another פסוק? pasuk? די
חיתימר הני
מילי, de-cheitemar hanei milei, maybe after four times God won't forgive you
בציבור be-tzibur in public, we've been talking about public and חילול השם
chillul Hashem etc., אבל ביחיד aval be-yachid לא
maybe as an individual God will forgive you even after four times.
תא שמע הן כל אלה יפעל אל פעמיים שלוש עם גבר hen
kol eleh yifa'al el pa'amayim shalosh im gaver with an individual. Now,
so what does this mean? So why won't he be forgiven the
fourth time? So you could say that basically what it means is
that after four times your תשובה teshuva isn't sincere and you keep
on falling back and you're not deserving of forgiveness, which is a
little bit harsh because I think so many people, the things that
they are working on, they could be working on their whole lives
and it's hard to say that what just because three יום כיפורים
Yom Kippurs you keep on backsliding the fourth time you're not going
to get forgiven? So it's worth noting that the גמרא Gemara did
not say if you did תשובה. teshuva. It just said God will
forgive. And רמב"ם Rambam actually, Mike was asking before about who knows
God's חשבונו, cheshbono, so I don't know the answer to that, but
on every the וידויים viduyim
we always say right, what do we say? מעביר ראשון ראשון, ma'avir
rishon rishon, right you pass away the first ones. So the רמב"ם
Rambam has this whole
idea sort of equation worked out. The first one, two things God
like doesn't even count them against you because yeah those are like
those are slip-ups. It only starts getting counted against you by number
three and then sometimes only by number four. So the רמב"ם Rambam
reads this גמרא Gemara not about if you've done תשובה. teshuva. If
you've done תשובה teshuva God will forgive you a million times. He
reads this גמרא Gemara that God will just automatically discount the first
one, two, three times and only start counting the fourth time. Now
it doesn't mean you completely forget the first few times, רמב"ם's Rambam
got a whole חשבון cheshbon that if you are punished then we're
going to go back and add them, but in terms of some
initial sense of a חשבון cheshbon we'll like sort of let the
first few times go before we start actually
taking you to account. So it is worth noting that רמב"ם Rambam
reads this גמרא Gemara to be without תשובה. teshuva. With תשובה teshuva
it's a different story because otherwise it would be a pretty scary
גמרא Gemara that if you slipped up three times you can no
longer do
תשובה teshuva after the fourth time, yeah. Well after three right anyway,
yeah.
Although if you read it in light of what we just saw
earlier, it would be the same exact circumstances, the same identical.
Well that could be too, so maybe you're saying that'll never happen,
maybe.
That'll never happen, but like you said.
Right, that could be.
Always doing the same story, even the same non-kosher, the same dish.
That it's the exact same thing is getting deeply ingrained. Right, until
you really work to un-ingrain it. Right, that's interesting.
So it's basically three
times and you're out you're saying.
Yeah right, three strikes is still okay, fourth strike. תנו רבנן, tanu
rabanan, עבירות שהתודה עליהם יום הכיפורים זה aveirot she-hitvada aleihem Yom HaKippurim
zeh so now talking about the idea about backsliding, but here actually
is somewhat of the opposite. עבירות שהתודה עליהם יום הכיפורים זה לא
יתודה עליהם יום הכיפורים אחר
aveirot she-hitvada aleihem Yom HaKippurim zeh lo yitvada aleihem
Yom HaKippurim acher that if you already did וידוי vidui then don't
bother going back to it on the next יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
you're done with it. You're not doing it anymore. ואם שנה בהם,
ve-im shana bahem, if you are now if you are going back
and you're still you've sinned again, then צריך להתודות יום הכיפורים אחר
tzarich lehitvadot Yom HaKippurim acher then clearly you need to do another
וידוי vidui presumably not just for this year's sins but for last
year's as well because clearly your וידוי vidui of last year wasn't
effective. But if you did וידוי vidui last year and you haven't
gone back to your old ways, then you can just move on,
which is very psychologically powerful, right? How long are you supposed to
be weighed down by your past sins? One of the amazing ideas
that יום כיפור Yom Kippur is מכפר, mechaper, why is יום כיפור
Yom Kippur מכפר mechaper as opposed to just תשובה? teshuva? Right, if
we want to think about it like we've been talking about ritual
and so on, like what's how would we explain the logic why
God will allow like just the day to be מכפר mechaper if
we haven't ourselves changed and or with a lesser degree of תשובה,
teshuva, what's that power? And part of the idea is because you
get totally weighed down with your sins and then it becomes you
become you lose the impetus to to be a better person and
you lose the impetus to to try to continue to grow. You
need that right balance of accountability without that sense of being completely
laden down with with guilt and the sense of how terrible you
are and you're such a sinner. So this is actually a very
healthy idea. It's like you know what, if you've done תשובה teshuva
and you haven't gone back and backslid and you've actually freed yourself
from that past behavior, move on with your life, don't let it
continue to weigh you down, it'll only be counterproductive. So that's the
first answer of the גמרא, Gemara, that's the first step of the
גמרא. Gemara. Then the גמרא Gemara says, I like that answer. Then
the גמרא Gemara says, ואם
לא שנה בהם וחזר והתודה ve-im lo shana bahem ve-chazar ve-hitvada and
if you did not repeat and you really freed yourself and you're
still going back and doing וידוי vidui you're still agonizing over it,
עליו הכתוב אומר alav hakatuv omer ככלב שב
על קיאו k'kelev shav al kiyo like a dog returning on its
vomit, like it's only going to do bad for you. You've done
תשובה, teshuva, move on with your life, okay? You really have freed
yourself from it. שונה באיוולתו, shoneh b'ivalto, כסיל שונה באיוולתו, k'sil shoneh
b'ivalto, that's a foolish man going back to his foolishness. You're just
bringing yourself back to that past identity, in a way maybe you're
even getting yourself back to that. Back into the mindset of sin.
You're a different person now, move on. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר,
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer, now Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says, כל
שכן שהוא משובח. kol she-ken she-hu meshubach. No, actually it's better if
you even after you've freed to go back and to do תשובה
teshuva about it again, שנאמר, shene'emar, כי פשעי אני אדע, ki fsha'ai
ani eda, my sins I will let be known, or I will
know, וחטאתי נגדי תמיד, vechatati negdi tamid, my sin is constantly in
front of me. אלא מה אני מקיים ככלב שב על קיאו? ella
ma ani mekayyem ki kelev shav al kei'o? What do you do
with the idea of a dog returning to its vomit? כי דרב
הונא, ki d'Rav Huna, דאמר רב הונא, d'amar Rav Huna, כיון שעבר
אדם עבירה ושנה בה, keivan she-avar adam aveira v'shanah bah, הותרה לו.
huttra lo. It doesn't mean you return to your vomit if you
do תשובה teshuva on it. You return to your vomit if you
continue doing the thing. That's what it is to return to your
vomit. So if and once you've done it once and twice, it's
now permitted to you. So the גמרא Gemara says, הותרה לו סלקא
דעתך? huttra lo salka da'atach? What, just because you've done it twice
now it's actually permitted? No, אלא אימא, ella eima, נעשה לו כהיתר.
na'aseh lo k'hetter. You become, you have so much learned to rationalize
your behavior that it no longer feels like an עבירה aveira anymore.
So the idea of going back to your vomit is not going
back and doing תשובה, teshuva, it's going back and repeating your sin.
That's what's the returning to your vomit. But doing תשובה, teshuva, even
after you've freed yourself from it, he says that's a good thing.
So again, you know, my
נשמה neshama goes out to the first approach, you know, as the
psycho, not just for me personally, but as the psychologically healthy one.
You know, I suppose that there's a proper balance, which is that
if you don't agonize over it, you know, I mean because there's
still a reality you did something wrong, especially what if it was
a בין אדם לחבירו bein adam l'chaveiro type of a sin, that
there's you know lasting repercussions about the acts that you've done and
so on. So you know, to sort of have that balance between,
you know, but to be sort of acknowledge it from afar as
opposed to be sort of agonized and immersed with a sense of
guilt, you know, and so on. I mean notice the גמרא Gemara
doesn't say it's a מצוה mitzvah to go back and to agonize
over it. It says there's a מצוה mitzvah to be חוזר והתוודה
עליה, chozer v'hitvadah aleiha, although the פסוק pasuk that it quotes is
וחטאתי נגדי תמיד vechatati negdi tamid does have that sense of like
constantly feeling terrible for your past sins. So you know, the first
approach does seem to be the more psychologically healthy, although the second
approach is quoted להלכה, l'halacha, but I think that the right balance
has to be struck between the two of them. Okay, yes?
Question from here in terms of this idea of this constant residue
of the generation or something?
Being punished for past sins, yeah.
Maybe, but you know I don't see that as being brought as
yeah that sense right of like collective punishment going through? Yeah, no,
but he's just saying the idea that we have like the sin
of you know חטא המרגלים cheit hamiraglim
resides and that the past sins you've done might carry on afterwards.
Yeah, I don't know, it's a good question. I think that I'd
rather leave that to the limited context in which we find that
because the גמרא, Gemara, you know, is much more about that sense
of like your personal, this is really much more shifting away from
the as you know like I said like you know in the
תורה Torah much more the sense of collective and communal and you
know and so on, and this is much more at the individual
level, so which I think, you know, resonates much more with us
today, yeah.
In the liturgical application of this first position is very helpful. In
other words, there are some נוסחאות nuschaot in which you say in
תחנון Tachanun a וידוי viduy every day. Right. So that יום כיפור
Yom Kippur in a way has been supported by an ongoing process
of being able to move through. You know what I mean, it's
not all a thousand tons falling on one day a year as
it were. You've already sort of acclimated yourself reflectively.
Right, right, right. יישר כוח. Yashar koach. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, וצריך לפרוט את
החטא. v'tzarich lifrot et hachet. Now when you do וידוי, viduy, you
have to detail the sin, you have to identify, list the things
that you've done wrong. Again, you know, that's obviously very important part
of owning up to the responsibility
and of not doing it again, you know, as opposed to doing
it in a very generic way. שנאמר, shene'emar, אנא חטא העם הזה
חטאה גדולה, ana chata ha'am hazeh chata'ah gedolah, this people has sinned
a great sin, ויעשו להם אלהי זהב, vaya'asu lahem elohei zahav, they
made gods of gold. So משה Moshe said explicitly. Of course that's
funny because that's more like a ritual וידוי, viduy, he's not he's
doing it for the people, you know, so now we're getting into
that again the question of תשובה teshuva versus ritual. דברי רבי יהודה
בן בבא. Divrei Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva
omer, אשרי נשוי פשע כסוי חטאה. ashrei nesuy pesha kesuy chata'ah. Now
praise is the one that covers the sin. And now this is
quite fascinating. This is even in the וידוי viduy between you and
God. This is not the discussion we had before about whether you're
supposed to let other people know about your תשובה teshuva and about
your sin. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says even between you and
God you don't you should not be listing it, which is quite
fascinating. Is it that he feels that that means that like by
listing it it's almost like a brazenness, you know, so therefore if
you're like so embarrassed you can't even say what you've If you
feel comfortable saying what you sinned, maybe it's a problem that you,
maybe there's too much of a sense of a brazenness to it.
Or maybe similar to discussions before he feels that you'll get so
weighed down by it, although here you really do understand it's hard
for it's hard to understand the idea of of saying you not
only are you not required but you actually even shouldn't in your
personal וידוי viduy mention the sins. אלא מה שאמר משה ויעשו להם
אלוהי זהב. Ella ma she'amar Moshe vaya'asu lahem elohei zahav. What does
it mean that Moshe said explicitly they made gods of gold? Why
did he say that? To, if you're not supposed to mention your
sins. To רב ינאי, Rav Yannai, like רב ינאי Rav Yannai דאמר
רב ינאי אמר משה לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא ריבונו של עולם,
de'amar Rav Yannai amar Moshe lifnei HaKadosh Baruch Hu Ribono
Shel Olam, כסף וזהב הרבית להם לישראל עד שאמרו די. kesef vezahav
hirbeita lahem leYisrael ad she'amru dai. You gave them so much gold
and silver until they said enough, enough. This is on the play
on the words ודי זהב Vedi Zahav in the beginning of דברים.
Devarim. די זהב Dai zahav enough gold. You gave them so much
gold and silver, גרם להם שיעשו אלוהי זהב. garam lahem sheya'asu elohei
zahav. You did it to them. You gave them so much gold
and silver. What are they supposed to do if not sin? So
that's why he said ויעשו להם אלוהי זהב. vaya'asu lahem elohei zahav.
It was all you. You gave them too much temptation. Okay, so
that's why he mentioned it, but not as part of the process
of וידוי. viduy. So here again a fascinating idea of רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva that you should not mention your sins during וידוי. viduy.
Not only are you not required, you should not. Again, maybe that
sense you should be so ashamed of them. It's hard to understand
exactly why you should not.
Even to a friend? Would you ask for מחילה? mechila?
No, presumably between you and God. If you have to ask מחילה,
mechila, you have to ask for something specific. Okay, next. שני פרנסים
טובים עמדו להם לישראל. Shenei parnasim tovim amdu lahem leYisrael. Now within
this discussion of mentioning sins, we're going to look at two examples.
שני פרנסים טובים עמדו להם לישראל. Shenei parnasim tovim amdu lahem leYisrael.
Two great sort of
sustainers, meaning like leaders, stood for the Jewish people. משה ודוד. Moshe
veDavid. Moshe and David. משה אמר יכתוב סורחני. Moshe amar yichtov sarchani.
Moshe says let my sin be written. שנאמר יען לא האמנתם בי
להקדישני לעיני בני ישראל. Shene'emar ya'an lo he'emantem bi lehakdisheni le'einei benei
Yisrael. It says what Moshe's sin was, that you did not, you
know, מי מריבה Mei Meriva and and you didn't sanctify me. דוד
אמר אל יכתוב סורחני. David amar al yichtov sarchani. David says, no,
I don't want my sin to be written. שנאמר אשרי נשוי פשע
כסוי חטאה. Shene'emar ashrei nesuy pesha kesuy chata'ah. Praised is one that
covers the sin. So right now what we're what we've been dealing
with, to say it, not say it, to do it, let it
be known in public or not let it be known. This is
sort of
being held up now as two contrasting models. But we're not going
to just leave it as two contrasting models. We're actually going to
try to reconcile them and see the reason behind them. Let's take
a look. משל דמשה ודוד למה הדבר דומה. Mashal deMoshe veDavid lema
hadavar domeh. What would be a good example of the case of
Moshe and David? דומה לשתי נשים שלקו בבית דין. Domeh lishtei nashim
shelaku beveit din. Two women were given lashes in the court. אחת
קילקלה, Achat kilkela, one really messed up, which means she committed adultery.
ואחת אכלה פגי שביעית, Ve'achat achla pigei shevi'it, and one did a
minor sin she ate unripe fruit on שמיטה Shemita before it was,
and it was considered like a waste of שמיטה Shemita produce. She
didn't wait for it to be ripe. Okay, so אמרה להן אותה
שאכלה פגי שביעית. Amra lahen otah she'achla pigei shevi'it. So the one
who ate the unripe fruit, did a minor sin, and she got
the same public embarrassment as the one who committed adultery. So she
said to the officers, she said, בבקשה מכם, Bevakasha mikem, please, do
me a favor. הודיעו על מה היא לוקה. Hodi'u al mah hi
loka. Let it be known on what she, meaning I, am receiving
lashes. I would like my sin to be made public, that I
got lashes for the eating of these unripe fruit. Why? שלא יאמרו
על מה שזו לוקה זו לוקה. Shelo yomru al mah shezo loka
zo loka. That I was, got lashes for the reason she got
lashes. They'll say I committed adultery too. I'd rather you let it
be known why I did it, so people should not associate me
with the same thing that she got. So הביאו פגי שביעית ותלו
בצווארה. Hevi'u pigei shevi'it vetalu betzavara. They took the figs and they
strung it around her neck. והיו מכריזין לפניה ואומרים. Vehayu machrizin lefaneia
ve'omrim. And they would make a big announcement and say, על עסקי
שביעית היא לוקה. Al iskei shevi'it hi loka. She is getting lashes
for שמיטה. Shemita. Now presumably meaning that Moshe's saying, look, I you
know I got this big punishment, David got this punishment, David got
this punishment for, I don't know, for committing adultery and sleeping with
בת שבע Bat Sheva and the whole thing with אוריה. Uriyah. I'd
rather you let it be known that my punishment was because I
spoke to the rock, or I hit the rock and didn't speak
to the rock. So it seems like it's contrasting to David. It
seems very clear. רש"י Rashi interestingly says that Moshe is saying it
to contrast it to the חטא chet of the דור המדבר. dor
hamidbar. That I shouldn't be said that I didn't go into ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael for the same reason they didn't go into ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. That my sin was less than their sin. But
again from the context of the גמרא Gemara it sounds like he's
contrasting it to David. Which then raises the interesting issue, like when
do you make the sins public, when don't you make the sins
public, have a lot to do with, like, you know, what's being
achieved by making it public? Is it bringing part of, though, this
is fascinating is that this is a concern not about God, not
about the larger sort of, you know, but about your own honor.
Like are you doing it to protect yourself to make it public
or are you doing it to protect yourself to make it private?
You know, what you have to do to respect your own honor,
which is an interesting thing to acknowledge. Like it's not like we
need the תשובה teshuvah process to lead to public humiliation, right? The
whole idea here is to preserve a sense of human dignity and
to give you that sense, it's not about complete self-abasement. It's in
order to give you the human dignity and the sense that you're
a good person and that you can move on and do תשובה
teshuvah and do better and so on. So thinking about this issue
of private and public just in the sense of preserving your own
dignity. And that is sort
of. also a
thing really important.
But nothing wrong with this judicial system.
Yeah, that they give the same
punishment for the
same...
people sent away for life for third-time marijuana and people and then
you get a slap on the wrist for what's supposed to be...
yeah anyway, anyway, פקיע שביעית Pakeish Shvi'is is only דרבנן d'rabanan and
מכת מרדות. makkas mardus. If it was real adultery, it would be
מיתת בית דין. misas Beis Din. So anyway, moving on.
רש"י Rashi follows the משל mashal a little bit closer in the
sense that there's two parties at the same time getting the same
punishment.
Right, by saying that it's משה Moshe and דור המדבר. Dor HaMidbar.
But when the גמרא Gemara set it up, it set it up
by saying, same way by משה Moshe and דוד, David, and didn't
tell you the דוד David part of it. Right? So I think
it's clear that, you know, again I understood why רש"י Rashi was
doing it, but רש"י Rashi ignores the whole דוד David part of
this. Okay now the גמרא Gemara continues, says like this: מפרסמים את
החנפים. mefarsmim es hachanafim. This is all a quote of a תוספתא.
Tosefta. מפרסמים את החנפים. mefarsmim es hachanafim. You publicize the sort of,
what's the word, the sycophants? How does it translate חנפים? hachanafim? The
people that are hypocrites? All right. Meaning people, מפני חילול השם. mipnei
chilul Hashem. It would be a desecration of God. Somebody goes around,
he acts like a צדיק, tzaddik, he's really this terrible disgusting person.
So are you supposed to out him? So actually, it's a fascinating
גמרא. Gemara. You have a responsibility to out him because of desecration
of God's
name, שנאמר, shenemar, ובשוב צדיק מצדקתו ועשה עול ונתתי מכשול לפניו. u’veshuv
tzaddik mitzidkato ve’asa avel unesati michshol lefanav. That if somebody does, who's
a צדיק tzaddik and presumably this person is presenting himself as a
צדיק, tzaddik, and he's doing perversion, God, I will cause him to
trip. Presumably I want it to be publicized, I don't want people
to be misled. If you look at רש"י, Rashi, right, רש"י Rashi
says, what does this mean? מפרסמים את החנפים. mefarsmim es hachanafim. רש"י
Rashi about ten lines down in the narrow lines in the second
column. רש"י Rashi says: שהם רשעים ומראין עצמן כצדיקים, אם יש מכיר
במעשיו מצווה לפרסמו מפני חילול השם. shehein resha’im umar’in atzman ketzaddikim, im
yesh makir bama’asav mitzvah lefarsemo mipnei chilul Hashem. I mean these things
happen, right? Somebody's going around and he has a leadership position, a
religious leadership position, and you know that this guy's a big hypocrite
and you know the nasty things he does. You should publicize it,
שלא ילמדו המתונים ממעשיו שסבורים עליו שהוא צדיק—that shelo yilmedu hamitunim mima’asav
shesvurim alav shehu tzaddik he's going to, you know, this type of
a person does not deserve to be serving in this role of
religious leadership. And you have a responsibility to, you know, it's sort
of like the rule, what is it, that there's like no libel,
you know, whatever, that there's a, you know, for like public figures?
Right? Isn't that the rule here in the States? Yeah, that there's
a—what? Much harder? Yes. Much harder, right. If you're a public figure,
anyway, so, you know, so well, yeah. But okay, anyway. But that's
quite, you know, but again, it's not like—it's not like saying this
guy is a sex abuser and therefore you have to prevent him
from, you know, from—from seeing people in private because he's go—you know,
like there's a direct one-to-one connection. It's just the fact that he—you
know what I'm saying? It's not like the thing that you know
about him he's direct—directly endangering people with. But it's just the fact
that you know he's a hypocrite and he has this position of
leadership and presumably even religious leadership means that he's a danger and
you have to protect people from that potential danger, which is quite
fascinating. Okay.
It does—those types of questions really do come up. All right, let's
get back to the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay. תשובת המוחלטין מעכבת הפורענות. teshuvat hamuchlatin me’akevet hapuranut. The תשובה teshuvah
even
about like dyed-in-the-wool people, people that are complete sinners, even they can
do תשובה teshuvah and that prevents punishment. ואף על פי שנחתם עליו
גזר דין של פורענות, v’af al pi shenichtam alav gzar din shel
puranut, even if it was already completely decided that they were going
to get punishment, their תשובה teshuvah works. שלוות רשעים סופת תקלה. shalvat
resha’im sofah takalah.
The fact that there is tranquility for the wicked—don't, you know, how
is it that bad people have it good? Don't worry, in the
end it will be their stumbling. They'll—it'll cause them to sin or
whatever, they'll get their comeuppance in the world to come. והרשות, ve’ha’rashus,
and positions of authority—this is a funny collection of statements, it's almost
a little פרקי אבות-ish. Pirkei Avot And positions of authority, מקברת את
בעליה—it mekaveret es be’aleha
will wind up burying the people that—that seize it. So positions of—of
leadership and authority, right. היזהר מן הרשות, hizaher min ha’rashus, right exactly.
עבירה מקלקלת את ה... aveira mekalkeles es ha...
well whatever. All right. ערום נכנס לה, arom nichnas lah, you will
go into these positions naked, וערום יצא ממנה, ve’arom yeitzei mimena, and
you will leave naked. Don't think you're going to come out decked
with all these royal clothes or whatever, they will strip you, they'll,
you know, they'll chew you up and spit you out alive. Okay.
לוואי שתהא יציאה כביאה, levai shetehei yetzia k’viah, you'll be lucky if
when you leave you're in as good of a shape as when
you entered it. רבי Rebbi
כי הוי נפיק ki hava nafik למידן דינא—רבי when he would go
out to sit in a court to be—to be a judge, אמר
הכי, amar hachi, he would say the
following: בצבו נפשי לקטלא bitzvu nafshi l’katla of the judgments that I
will pass, even if I God forbid pass a wrong judgment and
I'll be deserving of the punishment for having ruled incorrectly. וצבו ביתי
לית אנא עביד v'tzavu beiti leit ana avid
and I'm not even doing anything for my own house, like I'm
not even making any money off of this. I'm not helping myself,
I'm only exposing myself to punishment and danger in the doing of
this role. וריקם לביתי אזילנא v'reikam l'beiti azilna and I will go
back empty handed to my house. Like I'm not doing anything for
my own purpose, like when משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu says, לא חמור
אחד מהם נשאתי, lo chamor echad mehem nasati, the true leaders, all
they get is aggravation and criticism and so on and they're not
doing anything for themselves and they're accepting all of the burden of
responsibility.
Which was your rabbi's, what, yeah, ולואי שתהא ביאתי
כיציאתי.
v'luai shetehei biati k'yitziati. I'll only be so lucky if when I
come back home it'll be as good as when I left the
house. רבא Rava כי הוי נפיק same sort, רבא Rava when he
would go out לדינא l'dina אמר הכי amar hachi he said the
following: בצבו נפשי לקטלא נפיק betzavu nafshi lekatla nafik וצבו ביתי לית
אנא עביד וריקם לביתי אזילנא ולואי שתהא ביאתי כיציאתי v'tzavu beiti leit
ana avid v'reikam l'beiti azilna v'luai shetehei biati k'yitziati the same as
we said before. וכי הוי חזי אמבוה דבתריה v'ki hava chazi ambuha
d'basrei when he saw a crowd of people following him, אמר amar
he would say, אם יעלה לשמים שיאו im yaaleh l'shamayim seo if
the height goes up to heaven וראשו לעב יגיע v'rosho l'av yagia
his head goes up to the clouds, כגללו לנצח יאבד k'gilalo lanetzach
yovad
like a pile of dung he will ultimately be destroyed. So he
tried to humble
himself when the circumstances would happen it wouldn't go to his head.
ראיו יאמרו איו re'ov yomru ayo and everybody would say where is
he? Like people that thought they were so great in their lives,
nobody remembers them, they're just like a big pile of dung now.
רב זוטרא Rav Zutra כי הוי מכתפי ליה ki hava mechatafi lei
בשבתא דרגלא b'shabbata d'rigla
when רב זוטרא Rav Zutra they would carry him on the shoulders
on the שבת Shabbat of the רגל regel when he would go
out to give the public lecture, הוי אמר hava amar he would
say, he would try to tell himself from getting haughty, כי לא
לעולם חוסן ki lo l'olam chosen
property is not forever ואם נזר לדור דור v'im nezer l'dor dor
and a crown is not for future generations. שאת פני רשע לא
טוב se'et pnei rasha lo tov so now the lifting up the
face of the wicked is not good. לא טוב להם לרשעים lo
tov lahem l'rasha'im now we're going back to this idea of the
תוספתא Tosefta about how about the good things that happen to the
wicked, in the end it'll be their comeuppance. It's not good to
the wicked, so we're back to the earlier theme, שנושאים להם פנים
shenosim lahem panim בעולם הזה b'olam hazeh that they have it good
in this world. In the end that's gonna come back to bite
them. לא טוב לו לאחאב lo tov lo l'Achav שנושאו לו פנים
בעולם הזה. shenos'u lo panim b'olam hazeh. It wasn't good to אחאב
Achav that he had it good in this world, שנאמר, shene'emar, יען
כי נכנע לפני yaan ki nichna lefanai because
אחאב Achav has humbled himself before me, God allows his years to
be extended. But
although the years will be extended, לא אביא הרעה בימיו lo avi
hara'ah b'yamav I won't bring the evil in his day. I'll bring
it in his kids' day. So this gets back to the point
that David you were making that
the wicked people might not get punished but it's not going to
do them any good. In the end their future generations will get
it like double as a result. להטות צדיק במשפט l'hatot tzadik bamishpat
to incline for the righteous person the judgment. טוב להם לצדיקים tov
lahem l'tzadikim so that means to incline against them the judgment. טוב
להם לצדיקים שאין עושים להם פנים בעולם הזה tov lahem l'tzadikim she'ein
osim lahem panim b'olam hazeh it's good to the righteous that they
don't have it so good in this world. טוב לו למשה tov
lo l'Moshe שלא נשאו לו פנים בעולם הזה shelo nas'u lo panim
b'olam hazeh it was good that משה Moshe didn't have it good
in this world that he didn't go into the land. Why? That
he was not forgiven, that he was נשאו פנים nas'u panim also
means like he wasn't forgiven. It's good that he wasn't forgiven. He
got his punishment in this world so it doesn't carry on in
future generations.
שנאמר shene'emar as the פסוק pasuk says, יען לא האמנתם בי להקדישני
yaan lo heemantem bi l'hakdisheni
so therefore you won't bring the people in. ואילו האמנתם בי v'ilu
heemantem bi if you had believed in me and had acted properly,
ואילו לא הגיע זמנם ליפטר מן העולם v'ilu lo higia zmanam l'hipater
min ha'olam
you would not have died and you would have gone into the
land. But it was good that you got punished. Meaning again remember
נושא פנים nosei panim can mean to act favorably, but you remember
the theme I like talking about about נושא nosei to lift up
the sin. So the רשעים rasha'im if they're forgiven for the sin,
their account is still held over and their future generations are punished.
Whereas the
צדיקים tzadikim if they're punished for their sin, then it won't be
held over to future generations. So let's keep on reading about this.
That's the idea. Do you want to get paid up now or
do you want all your future generations to suffer? אשריהם לצדיקים ashreihem
l'tzadikim praise are the righteous. לא דיין שהן זוכין lo dayan shehen
zochin not only do
they merit, אלא שמזכין לבניהם ולבני בניהם עד סוף כל הדורות. ela
shemazakin livneihem v'livnei v'neihem ad sof kol hadorot. The merit they do
is for all future generations. שכמה בנים היו לו לאהרן שראויים לישרף
כנדב ואביהוא. shekama banim hayu lo l'Aharon sherauyim l'hisaref k'Nadav v'Avihu. אהרן
Aharon had a couple of sons that should have been burned, meaning
אלעזר Elazar ואיתמר v'Itamar also should have been burned when נדב Nadav
ואביהוא v'Avihu were burned. שנאמר shene'emar הנותרים hanotarim it says the remaining
sons, which is understood to mean that they were left over but
they were deserving of being burned, presumably because they went up and
they saw had that vision of God at the end of פרשת
משפטים. Parshat Mishpatim. etcetera. אלא שעמד להם זכות אביהם, ela she-amad la-hem
zchut avi-hem,
but because Aaron, you know, he bequeathed his merit to future generations.
So there, the רשעים resha'im pass down their debts, pass down their
you know, their punishment to future generations. The צדיקים, tzadikim, they get
punished for their sins now, and they pass down their merits to
future generations. Okay, אוי לרשע, oy la-rasha, woe to the wicked. לא
דיין שמחייבין עצמן, lo dayyan she-mchayvin atzman, not only do they make
themselves, you know, do they bring punishment upon themselves, אלא שמחייבין לבניהם
ולבני בניהם עד סוף כל הדורות, ela she-mchayvin li-vneihem u-li-vnei vneihem ad
sof kol ha-dorot, they bring the punishment to future generations. הרבה בנים
היו לו לכנען שראויים לסמוך כטבי עבדו של רבן גמליאל. harbe banim
hayu lo l-khna'an she-re'uyim l-ismoch k-tevi avdo shel raban gamliel. You know,
כנען Kna'an would have had many descendants that would have been fit
to receive סמיכה smicha like טבי, Tevi, right? טבי Tevi was the
slave of רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. All slaves were seen as descendants
of כנען, Kna'an, and he was a huge תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham.
So כנען Kna'an had many descendants that could have been huge תלמידי
חכמים talmidei chachamim and could have had סמיכה. smicha. אלא שחובת אביהם
גרמה להם, ela she-chovat avihem garma lahem,
but because of כנען's Kna'an sin, it got passed down to future
generations. So basically the point being that the רשעים resha'im have it
good sometimes in this world, yes, but they pass down all of
the punishment, don't worry, their descendants, as it's an interesting shift. Normally
we say they'll get it in עולם הבא. olam ha-ba. Now actually
saying no no no, their descendants will get it in עולם הזה.
olam ha-ze.
I don't know, the children will be punished, like פוקד עוון אבות.
poked avon avot. It seems to be to go back to the
point made before, those accounts will be held over and all future
generations will suffer as a result, whereas the צדיקים, tzadikim, they'll get
punished, but the result will be that they get to hold over.
What do you, maybe he has a good model, since we've spoken
about the whole model of debt. What do you collecting interest on?
So if you pay up all of your debt, then you keep
your credits in the bank and you get interest on your credits
and therefore that interest gets inherited to future generations, whereas if you
get all of your reward in this world, then all of your
debts are a loan and you keep on paying interest in future
generations.
All
right, fine. כל המזכה, kol ha-mizakeh, anyway but that's the metaphor. The
metaphor is are you holding over your merits and then everybody's getting
interest off your merits, are you holding over your debts and they're
all continuing to pay the interest on your debts? כל המזכה את
הרבים אין חטא בא על ידו, kol ha-mizakeh et ha-rabim ein chet
ba al yado,
anybody who brings merit to the masses does not
will not be you know stumble in sin. וכל המחטיא את הרבים,
ve-chol ha-machti et ha-rabim, if somebody causes the masses to sin, כמעט,
kim'at, interesting, כמעט kim'at אין מספיקין בידו לעשות תשובה. ein maspikin b-yado
la'asot teshuvah.
So even when we're talking about the whole divine justice here and
equaling the accounts, we don't want to completely discount the efficacy of
תשובה. teshuvah. So if you cause the masses to sin, practically you
won't have an opportunity to do תשובה. teshuvah.
I know, I know.
And those start here,
I
don't know if we have that. Some say that you don't actually
גורס gores כמעט. kim'at. I understand. כל המזכה kol ha-mizakeh but with
our גירסא girsa of כמעט, kim'at, I think it's powerful that they
don't want to completely discount תשובה. teshuvah. כל המזכה את הרבים אין
חטא בא על ידו, kol ha-mizakeh et ha-rabim ein chet ba al
yado, מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, why? כדי שלא יהא הוא בגיהנום ותלמידיו
בגן עדן. k-dei she-lo yehe hu b-gehinnom v-talmidav b-gan eden. You shouldn't
be in גיהנום gehinnom and everybody that I brought merit to is
getting גן עדן. gan eden. שנאמר כי לא תעזוב נפשי לשאול לא
תתן חסידך לראות שחת. she-ne'emar ki lo ta'azov nafshi l-sh'ol lo titen
chasidcha lir'ot shachat. You will not abandon my soul to the netherworld,
you won't allow your righteous to see the destruction. וכל המחטיא את
הרבים אין מספיקין בידו לעשות תשובה. ve-chol ha-machti et ha-rabim ein maspikin
b-yado la'asot teshuvah. Here it doesn't have the word כמעט. kim'at. You
don't but even there it doesn't say it says you don't give
him the opportunity to do תשובה. teshuvah. It doesn't say that if
he does תשובה teshuvah it won't be effective. Even without the word
כמעט, kim'at, it does not say that תשובה teshuvah is not effective.
It says you don't provide he won't have the opportunity to do
תשובה. teshuvah. שלא יהא הוא בגן עדן ותלמידיו בגיהנום. she-lo yehe hu
b-gan eden v-talmidav b-gehinnom. Again, that would be completely unjust if he
would be in גן עדן gan eden and everybody he brought sin
upon would be in גיהנום. gehinnom. שנאמר אדם עשוק בדם נפש עד
בור ינוס אל יתמכו בו. she-ne'emar adam ashuk b-dam nefesh ad bor
yanus al yitmechu vo. He will go down into the well, no
one will give him support. Okay, tomorrow God willing if we can
keep up that pace we will finish the מסכת. masechet. All right.